He dared to dream, he dared to love.
The Hunchback of Notre Dame is a drama, animation,
family film directed by Gary Trousdale.
Isolated bell-ringer Quasimodo wishes to leave Notre Dame tower against the wishes of Judge
Claude Frollo, his stern guardian and Paris' strait-laced Minister of Justice.
His first venture to the outside world finds him Esmeralda, a kind-hearted and
fearless Romani woman who openly stands up to Frollo's tyranny.
Quasimodo (voice), played by Tom Hulce.
Esmeralda (voice), played by Demi Moore.
Phoebus (voice), played by Kevin Kline.
Frollo (voice), played by Tony Jay.
Gargoyle Victor (voice), played by Charles Kimbrough.
Gargoyle Laverne (voice), played by Mary Wickes.
The Hunchback of Notre Dame is a 1996 American animated medieval period musical film loosely based
on the 1831 novel by Victor Hugo, and produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation.
Directed by Gary Trousdale and Kirk Wise, produced by Don Hahn, and written by Tab Murphy, Irene Mecchi, Jonathan Roberts, and the writing team of Bob Tzudiker and Noni White, the film stars Tom Hulce, Demi Moore, Tony Jay, and Kevin Kline, the film follows Quasimodo (Hulce),
the deformed and confined bell-ringer of Notre Dame, and his yearning to explore the outside world and be accepted by society, against the wishes of his cruel, puritanical adoptive father Claude Frollo (Jay), who also wants to exterminate Paris' Romani population.
In 1993, David Stainton, then a development executive at Disney Feature Animation,
conceived the idea to adapt Victor Hugo's Gothic novel into an animated feature.
He subsequently pitched the idea to then-Disney
Studios chairman Jeffrey Katzenberg.
At Katzenberg's request, Trousdale, Wise, and Hahn joined the project in 1993.
Murphy wrote the first draft of the script, and Mecchi and Roberts, who had
rewritten the script for The Lion King (1994), were soon brought in.
Additional rewrites were provided by Tzudiker and White.
That same year, the production team embarked on a research trip to Paris to study
the Notre-Dame cathedral and additional locations for the film.
The musical score was composed by Alan Menken, with songs
written by Menken and lyricist Stephen Schwartz.
The Hunchback of Notre Dame premiered at the Louisiana Superdome in New Orleans on
June 19, 1996, and was released in the United States on June 21.
The film received generally positive reviews and was a commercial success, grossing over
$325 million worldwide and becoming the fifth highest-grossing film of 1996.
Despite the film's changes made from the original source material and adding comedic elements to ensure a G rating from the MPAA, it remains more mature and
darker than any Disney animated films with approach to thematic elements, including themes of genocide, lust, prejudice, sin, and redemption.
A stage adaptation of the film was produced by Walt Disney Theatrical in 1999.
A direct-to-video sequel, The Hunchback of Notre Dame II, was released in 2002.
The film explores themes of dance, paris, france,
based on novel or book, judge, sword.
The tone is emotional.